okay let's practice using solubility
product constant fluorite or CaF2 is
slightly water soluble and dissolves
according to the following equation so
we have fluoride solid in equilibrium
with the calcium 2 plus ion and 2
fluoride ions now a saturated fluoride
solution is measured as having a calcium
ion concentration of 2.1 times 10 to the
negative 4 molar so what is the
solubility product for fluorite so
that's all the information we need go
ahead and give this a try.
so let's put
our equilibrium up top and once again we
know that the calcium ion concentration
is 2.1 times 10 to the negative 4 molar
so what can we do with this information
well we know that fluorite is going to
dissolve to give a calcium ion and to
fluoride ions so if enough fluoride has
dissolved so as to give a calcium ion
concentration of that magnitude then we
know that the fluoride ion concentration
must be double that because there are
two fluorides that form for every
calcium ion so that means the fluoride
ion concentration must be 4.2 times 10
to the negative 4 molar right that has
exactly double the calcium ion
concentration so we figured that out
just by stoichiometry now let's write
our Ksp expression so this is just like
any other equilibrium expression it
involves only aqueous or gaseous species
and so that means we're just going to
have the calcium ion concentration times
the fluoride ion concentration squared
and then we don't have to put that over
any reactants because the reactant is a solid
now we have all the information we need
we have the calcium ion concentration
and we have the fluoride ion
concentration so we just plug those
numbers in and then we do the arithmetic
and we get a Ksp value of three point
seven times ten to the negative eleven.